宇宙大探索
第三集
我们的身世很神秘
We were born into a mystery
这一直困扰着我们
one that has haunted us
自从人类诞生就是如此
since at least as long as we've been human.
在这个星空覆盖下的小星球上
We awakened on this tiny world
我们开始有了意识
beneath a blanket of stars,
就如同被遗弃在门口的婴儿
like an abandoned baby left on a doorstep
没有留下只字词组
without a note to explain
告诉我们是谁 我们从哪里来
where we came from, who we are,
我们的世界会是怎样
how our universe came to be.
我们在宇宙中是否还有其它同类
And with no idea how to end our cosmic isolation.
我们必须自己找出答案
We've had to figure it all out for ourselves.
我们最大的财富
Best thing we had going for us
就是我们的智慧
was our intelligence,
特别是识别规律的天赋
especially our gift for pattern recognition,
经过远古以来进化过程的改造
sharpened over eons of evolution.
那些擅长区分猎物和猛兽的人
The ones who were good at spotting prey and predator,
擅长识别有毒的食物的人
telling poisonous plants from the nourishing ones,
他们活下去并繁衍的几率更大
they had a better chance to live and reproduce.
他们幸存下来 并把识别规律的基因传下去
They survived and passed on those genes for pattern recognition
优势显而易见
with its obvious advantages.
地球上的不同文化
Cultures all over the planet
都是仰望同一个星空
looked up at the same stars
然后做出不同的解读
and found different pictures there.
我们用这种天赋在自然界中寻找规律
We used this gift for recognizing patterns in nature
解读天空中的年历
to read the calendar in the sky.
写在星空中的信息
The messages written in the stars
告诉我们的祖先
told our forefathers and mothers
何时安营  何时启程
when to camp and when to move on.
兽群何时迁徙
When the migratory herds
何时下雨  何时天寒
and when the rains and the cold would come.
何时他们可以停下来休息
And when they would cease for a time.
当他们观察恒星间的运动与地球上
When they observed the direct connection between the motions of the stars
生命周期变化之间的直接联系
and the seasonal cycles of life on Earth,
他们很自然地得出结论
they concluded, naturally,
天上发生的变化
that what happens up there
必然和地球上发生的事情息息相关
must be directed at us down here.
也有道理 对吧
It makes sense, right?
如果把天空看成日历
If the sky was a calendar
有人在上面贴上一张便签纸
and somebody stuck a Post-it note on top of it,
除了传达信息还会是什么
what else could it be but a message?
所以  当天空的秩序被突然打破时
And so, when the heavenly order was suddenly violated
比如 当彗星划过天际时
by the apparition of a comet in the sky...
人们就会和自身联系起来
they took it personally.
也不能怪他们
Can we really blame them?
那时 对于所发生的事情也没有其它
Back then, they had no other logical explanation
符合逻辑的解释
for what was happening.
那是很久以前
This was long before
没人会认为地球是个
anyone had yet to imagine Earth
倾斜自转的行星
as a spinning planet with a tilted axis,
绕着太阳公转
revolving around the Sun.
每种文化中的古人都犯过相同的错误
Every ancient human culture made the same mistake,
彗星一定是来自众神
a comet must be a message,
或某一个神的旨意
sent by the gods... or one particular god.
几乎是必然的  我们的祖先认为
And almost invariably, our ancestors concluded
大事不妙
the news was not good.
不论你是古阿兹特克人
It didn't matter if you were an ancient Aztec,
古英国人 古巴比伦人  古印度人
Anglo-Saxon, Babylonian, Hindu.
彗星都是毁灭的前兆
Comets were portents of doom.
仅有的不同是
The only difference among them
灾难预报的精确程度
was the precise nature of the coming disaster.
灾祸 源自希腊语中的 灾星
"Dis-aster," as in the Greek word for "bad star."
对东非的马塞人来说
To the Masai of East Africa,
彗星意味着饥荒
a comet meant famine.
对南非的祖鲁人来说
To the Zulu in the south,
意味着战争
it meant war.
对于西非的迦纳人来说
To the Eghap people of the west,
意味着瘟疫
it meant disease.
对扎伊尔人来说
To the Djaga of Zaire,
扎伊尔人（刚果）
特指 天花
specifically "smallpox."
对于他们的邻居 陆巴人
To their neighbors, the Luba,
彗星预示着领袖之死
a comet foretold the death of a leader.
古代中国人有着惊人的系统分类
The ancient Chinese were remarkably systematic.
大约公元前1400年
Starting in roughly 1400 BC,
他们就开始了对彗星的
they began recording and cataloguing
记录和分类
the apparitions of comets.
三尾彗星
A three-tailed comet
意味着国家的灾难
meant calamity for the state.
四尾彗星
A four-tailed comet
标志着瘟疫降临
signified an epidemic was coming.
人类识别规律的天赋
The human talent for pattern recognition
是把双刃剑
is a two-edged sword.
我们尤其擅长寻找规律
We're especially good at finding patterns,
哪怕无中生有
even when they aren't really there--
或者 牵强附会
something known as "false pattern recognition."
我们渴望证明
We hunger for significance,
人类的存在对这个宇宙
for signs that our personal existence
有着重大的意义
is of special meaning to the universe.
说到底 我们的渴望
To that end, we're all too eager
使我们宁愿相信
to deceive ourselves and others,
烤面包上出现的圣像
to discern a sacred image in a grilled cheese sandwich
或者彗星带着上帝的旨意
or find a divine warning in a comet.
今天 我们已经
Today, we know exactly where comets come from
清楚知道了彗星的本质
and what they're made of.
我们的想象之舟
Our Ship of the Imagination,
由科学和好奇共同驱动
fueled by equal parts of science and wonder,
可以带我们游历任何时空
can take us anywhere in space and time.
可以走的比光速还快
It can travel faster than light
可以呈现肉眼无法看见的事物
and render visible those things that cannot be seen.
将我们进入一条神秘的溪流
It's carrying us to a mysterious realm
距离太阳一光年的地方
that lies one light-year from the Sun.
众多的星体为何聚集
What is this swarm of worlds?
是由外星生物安排的吗
Was it organized by alien beings?
不是
No.
万有引力而已
Just gravity.
历年的积雪
These are the snows of yesteryear,
山峰般的寒冰和岩石
drifting mountains of ice and rock,
太阳系诞生时的剩余产物
the preserved remnants of the birth of the solar system.
组成了 奥尔特云团
It's called the Oort Cloud,
以荷兰天文学家奥尔特命名
after Jan Oort, the Dutch astronomer
他在1950年就预言了这个云团的存在
who foretold its existence back in 1950.
他原本想解决一个悖论
He was trying to solve a paradox.
彗星有很多种消亡的方式
There's so many ways for comets to die.
因为他们会穿过行星的轨道
Because they cross the orbits of planets,
经常发生碰撞
comets frequently collide with them.
彗星很大程度上由冰组成
Comets are largely made of ice,
所以 每次接近太阳时
so every time they come near the Sun,
他们会蒸发掉一部分
they lose a part of themselves through evaporation.
这个过程重复几千次
And after several thousand trips,
所有的冰 蒸发了
their ice is all gone,
残余的彗星就是现在的小行星
and what remains of the comet is now an asteroid.
彗星被太阳系的引力场排斥
Comets can be gravitationally ejected from the solar system
流放至太空
and exiled into space.
无论如何
And yet, somehow,
彗星总会回来
the comets keep coming.
奥尔特和其它天文学家自忖
Oort and other astronomers wondered,
这些彗星都是哪里来的
"Where do all the comets come from?"
奥尔特通过计算新彗星出现的比率
Oort calculated the rate at which new comets appear
得出结论
and concluded that there must be
由数量极多的彗星组成一个
a vast, spherical swarm of them,
直径达到几光年的
a few light-years across,
园球状包围太阳
surrounding the Sun.
奥尔特的理论时至今日依然成立
Oort's logic still holds up,
哪怕是几十年后  我们对彗星和太阳系
even after all the discoveries we've made about comets
有了更多的认识的今天
and the solar system in the many decades since.
不过  奥尔特云团是个
And yet, the Oort Cloud is a sight
无人能看到的景象
that no one has ever seen.
我们也不行
Nor could we.
那里漆黑一片
It's dark out here.
最近的两个彗星间的距离就如同
And each comet is about as far from its closest neighbor
地球到土星的距离
as the Earth is from Saturn.
但是 科学给我们特殊的能力
But science gives us special powers of our own.
科学给了奥尔特
It gave Jan Oort
预见的天赋
the gift of prophecy.
奥尔特也是第一个正确估计出
Oort was also the first to correctly estimate
太阳到银河系中心的距离
the distance between the Sun and the center of our galaxy.
这是很了不起的成就
That's a big deal--
找到了我们在银河系的位置
finding out where we are in the Milky Way.
我们的恒星
Our star is about
距离中心3万光年
30,000 light-years from the center.
奥尔特也是首个
Oort was also
使用射电望远镜
the first guy to use a radio telescope
绘制出了银河系的螺旋结构
to map the galaxy's spiral structure.
并且 他发现银河系的中心
And he discovered that the center of our galaxy
发生着一连串极大的爆炸
was a place of titanic explosions,
这是第一个迹象 显示出那里可能
the first indication that there might have been
暗藏着一个巨大的黑洞
a supermassive black hole lurking there.
事实上 我们中的很多人
Does the fact that most of us know
知道著名杀人魔的名字
the names of mass murderers,
却从没听说过奥尔特
but never heard of Jan Oort,
人性就是如此
say anything about us?
奥尔特云团是如此巨大
The Oort Cloud is so enormous
彗星要用100万年
that it takes one of its comets about a million years
才能绕太阳一圈
to complete a single trip around the Sun.
在这里 太阳系的边缘
Out here, at the far edge of the solar system,
即使擦肩而过的星星产生的轻微引力
even a little tug from the gravity of a passing star
也会使这些彗星
can liberate some of these comets
摆脱太阳引力的束缚
from their gravitational bondage to the Sun.
一些彗星被抛出太阳系
Some comets are flung out of the solar system
从此在星际空间游荡
to wander interstellar space.
其它的一些彗星 却有着不同的命运
But for others, there's a different fate.
这颗彗星被抛向太阳
This one is plunging towards the Sun,
在无阻力的自由落体中不断加速
gaining speed in an unbroken free fall
一直持续几十万年
that lasts hundreds of thousands of years.
当海王星的引力再次吸引它时
When Neptune's gravity gives it another tug,
它的轨迹发生了小小的变化
there's a small change in course.
强大的木星
Mighty Jupiter, the most massive
太阳系中质量最大的物体
object in our solar system--
除太阳以外
other than the Sun-- attracts the comet
用它强大的引力再次改变彗星的轨迹
with its powerful gravitational pull, bending its path.
当这颗彗星到达太阳系的核心
When our comet reaches the inner solar system...
太阳的热量烘烤着它
heat from the Sun bakes it.
一场美丽的转变开始了
A beautiful transformation begins.
被烟熏黑的贫瘠冰山
The barren, sooty iceberg
变幻出灼热的光晕
now sports a glowing halo...
还有彗尾
and a tail.
这些粉尘层描述着大约40亿年前
These layers tell the story of how the comet was made,
彗星产生的过程
some four billion years ago.
在4万代人的历史中
During the 40,000 generations of humanity,
至少有大约10万次
there must have been roughly 100,000 apparitions
耀眼的彗星划过天际
of a bright comet.
那个时候
For all that time,
我们只能仰望  不禁的惊叹
the best we could do was look up in helpless wonder,
无助的人们不知所措
prisoners of Earth with nowhere to turn
除了恐惧和悔恨 没有更好的办法
for an explanation beyond our guilt and our fears.
后来 两个人的友情为人类的思想
But then a friendship began between two men that led
带来了翻天覆地的革命
to a permanent revolution in human thought.
艾萨克・牛顿和爱德蒙・哈雷 也是始料未及
Isaac Newton and Edmond Halley could not know it,
他们的研究成果将我们从
but their collaboration would ultimately set us free
这颗小星球的局限中彻底解放
from our long confinement on this tiny world.
1664年的这颗彗星
The Comet of 1664
令整个欧洲恐惧颤栗
sent shivers of dread throughout Europe,
随后发生的大瘟疫和伦敦大火灾
and the terror seemed justified when the Plague
恰巧印证了人们的恐惧
and the Great Fire of London followed soon after.
那血色的长发
There, with long bloody hair,
耀眼的星辰威胁整个世界
a blazing star threatens the world
带来饥荒  瘟疫 战争
with famine, plague and war.
王子们的死亡
To princes, it spells death...
王国多了无数的墓碑
to kingdoms, many crosses...
不可避免的财产损失
to all estates, inevitable losses...
腐烂的牧群
to herdsmen, rot,
颗粒无收的庄稼汉
to plowmen, hapless seasons,
海上的风暴
to sailors, it brings storms,
暴动的市民
to cities, civil treasons.
但有一个孩子
But for one child,
并不觉得彗星有那么恐怖
the comet was not the least bit frightening.
对他来说 只是惊奇
For him, it was a thing of wonder.
和我们一样  爱德蒙・哈雷生性好奇
Like all of us, Edmond Halley was born curious.
哇塞
Hell's bells!
他很幸运  他的父亲支持并鼓励他的求知欲
He was lucky to have a father who encouraged and nurtured his curiosity,
给他买了最好的科学仪器
buying him the best scientific instruments
资助他的探险考察
and even funding his expedition
为了画出第一张精确的南半球星空图
to make the first accurate star map of the Southern Hemisphere.
哈雷20岁时从牛津辍学
Halley dropped out of Oxford when he was 20,
去了圣赫勒拿岛
and sailed to St. Helena,
一个位于赤道以南  非洲的西海岸的小岛
an island below the equator, off the west coast of Africa.
哇塞
Hell's bells.
问题是 没人告诉哈雷
The problem was, nobody told Halley
岛上的天气状况是如此糟糕
that the weather on St. Helena was generally lousy;
他用了12个月
it took him 12 frustrating months
才观测到足够的南半球星星来绘制完整的星图
to observe enough southern stars to make a complete map.
古希腊的众神和英雄人物
The gods and heroes of ancient Greece were now joined
由虚构的图形将他们汇聚在一起
by the mythic figures of a new world and age,
巨喙鸟  指南针  天堂鸟
a toucan, a compass, a bird of paradise.
当哈雷带着《南天星表》回到家时
When Halley came home with the other half of the sky,
他的星空图造成了轰动
his map created a sensation.
商人和探险家可以根据随处可见的星星导航
Now merchants and explorers could navigate by the stars visible anywhere on Earth.
当时 伦敦的皇家学会
At the time, the World Society of London
是世界上科学发现的集散地
was the world's clearinghouse of scientific discovery.
它的格言是 不人云亦云
Its motto, "Nullius in verba,"
总结出了科学方法的中心思想
sums up the heart of the scientific method.
它是拉丁语中的 亲自求证
It's Latin for "see for yourself."
换言之 质疑权威
In other words, "question authority."
哈雷的星图引起了学会实验室负责人的注意
Halley's star maps caught the attention of the Society's Curator of Experiments.
我也想让你看看他的样子
I'd show him to you if I could,
但罗伯特・胡克并没有留下任何的肖像画
but no portrait of Robert Hooke exists from his time,
只有他的事迹口耳相传
only the verbal descriptions of his contemporaries.
他们说他 瘦弱 驼背 丑陋
They called him "lean, bent, ugly."
他可能是最有创造性的天才
He was possibly the most inventive person who ever lived.
不论他的外表如何
And despite his appearance,
他在当时的伦敦炙手可热
he was the most sought-after party guest in all of London.
为何
Why?
因为胡克永不满足的求知欲
Hooke's insatiable curiosity
覆盖了所有的领域
encompassed absolutely everything.
胡克发现了一个小宇宙
Hooke discovered a little cosmos,
我们至今沿用他给它的命名  细胞
and we still call it by the name he gave it, the cell.
单词原意：单人房
胡可通过观察一片软木片发现了细胞
Hooke discovered the cell by looking
正是用了他自己的一项发明
at a piece of cork with one of his own inventions,
复合显微镜
the compound microscope.
他提出的观点比达尔文的进化论
He anticipated aspects of Darwin's theory of evolution
早了几乎200年
by almost 200 years.
胡克又改良t望远镜
Hooke also improved the telescope.
他根据观察天体所做的素描
The drawings he made of the astronomical bodies he observed
见证了他异乎寻常的准确性
attest to his uncanny precision.
1666年的伦敦大火灾摧毁了伦敦中部
After the Great Fire destroyed central London in 1666,
胡克与建筑师 克里斯多佛・雷恩合作
Hooke partnered with the architect Christopher Wren
重新设计 建设 伦敦
to redesign and rebuild the city.
胡克是当时首屈一指的实验主义者
Hooke was the foremost experimentalist of his age.
使用弹簧
Using coiled springs,
他提出了 弹性定律
he derived the "law of elasticity,"
我们称之为  胡克定律
known today as Hooke's Law.
他改良了气泵
He perfected the air pump,
达到了当时的技术顶峰
the height of technology in its time,
并将之用于声音和呼吸实验
and used it to experiment on respiration and sound.
他用大麻做实验
And he experimented with cannabis.
他在一次皇家学会的会议上报告
He reported to a meeting of the Royal Society
据他的一位船长朋友说
that a sea captain friend of his
「经常食用这个东西
"had so often experimented with it,
不会令人产生恐惧
that there is no cause of fear,
只会带来喜悦」
though possibly there may be of laughter."
咖啡在17世纪的英格兰
But coffee was the drug of choice for England
是最受欢迎的
in the 17th century.
咖啡馆遍布伦敦
Coffeehouses sprang up all over London.
人们在那里获取新闻
This is where people came to get news,
发表新的观点 讨论时事
to launch new ventures, and to debate ideas.
咖啡馆是这个注重阶级的社会中
The coffeehouse was an oasis of equality
平等的绿洲
in a class-obsessed society.
在这里  穷人不需要给富人让座
Here, a poor man needn't give up his seat
也不用屈从他的观点
to a rich man, nor submit to his opinion.
就像是民主制度的实验室
It was a kind of laboratory of democracy.
在这种高度兴奋刺激的气氛中
In this highly caffeinated atmosphere,
哈雷和胡克 与克里斯多佛・雷恩讨论着一个谜团
Halley and Hooke met Christopher Wren to discuss a deep mystery.
为何行星如此运动
Why do the planets move as they do?
天文学家约翰内斯・开普勒在此前的
The astronomer Johannes Kepler had demonstrated,
80多年 就证明了
some 80 years before,
行星绕太阳公转的轨道
that the orbits of the planets around the Sun
并不是正圆  而是椭圆形
were not perfect circles, but actually ellipses,
行星越靠近太阳
and that the closer a planet was to the Sun,
运动的越快
the faster it moved.
为什么
Why?
会是太阳发出某些看不见的力量 导致这种变化吗
Could some invisible force from the Sun be responsible for this change in motion?
如果是  又是如何导致的呢
If so, how did it work?
可以用一个简单的数学定律描述吗
Could there be a simple mathematical law to describe it?
就像胡克的弹性定律那样
Maybe something like Hooke's Law of Elasticity?
有可能
Perhaps.
但是 尝试之后
But try as he might,
克里斯多佛・雷恩没有答案
Christopher Wren couldn't figure it out.
总好过没有尝试过
Damned if I haven't tried.
我的能力有限
It's beyond me.
我押上这本价值40先令的书
I'll wager a book worth 40 shillings
谁能解决 谁就拿去
to the man who can solve it!
我拿定了  雷恩先生
That book is mine, Mr. Wren.
我已经完成了计算
I've already done the calculation.
哈雷非常开心
Halley was delighted.
快让我们见识见识  胡克先生
Show us, Mr. Hooke.
但几个月过去  胡克也没能做到
But months passed, and Hooke failed to deliver.
他算不过来
He couldn't do the math.
没人能够
None of them could.
最后 哈雷厌烦了胡克的借口
Finally, Halley had enough of Hooke's excuses.
哈雷知道 肯定在某个地方 有某个人
Halley knew there must be someone, somewhere,
可以做到
up to the challenge.
剑桥大学的数学家怎么样
What about that mathematician at Cambridge?
聪明的家伙
Clever fellow.
他多年前就解决了光线本质的核心问题
He had solved central questions about the nature of light
他当时只有22岁
years before, when he was still only 22.
他发明了反射望远镜
And he invented the reflecting telescope.
怪人
Odd bird.
销声匿迹过一段时间
Dropped out of sight a while back;
对胡克本人和他的光学理论有些不同看法
some squabble over Hooke and his discovery about light.
走了极端  无法自拔
Went completely to pieces over it
从此在剑桥大学隐居
and has been hiding out in Cambridge ever since.
哈雷很期待 这个怪人
Halley wondered if this strange, and by all accounts,
据说 很难相处的人
exceedingly difficult man, might succeed
是否能成功
where Hooke and others had failed.
他当时并不知道
What he couldn't know,
没有任何人会想到
what no one could possibly imagine at the time,
整个世界
were the countless ways
就在1684年8月的某一天
the world would be forever changed by this meeting
各个方面都因为这次见面 从此改变
on an August day in 1684.
艾萨克・牛顿出生于英格兰
Isaac Newton was born in England
1642年的圣诞节
on Christmas Day in 1642.
父亲在他出生前就过世了
Before he even opened his eyes, his father was already dead.
3岁时 母亲也抛弃了他
His mother left him when he was only three
直到11岁才再次见面
and did not return until he was 11.
她已经有了新的家庭
When she did, it was with a new family and husband,
牛顿鄙视他的继父
a stepfather who Isaac Newton despised.
悲惨家庭环境中的唯一避风港
Newton's refuge from his miserable family life
就是牛顿对于科学研究的热情
was his passion to understand how things worked,
特别是自然科学
especially nature itself.
1661年  天资聪颖的艾萨克进了剑桥大学三一学院
In 1661, the talented young Isaac entered Trinity College at Cambridge University
他在学校很不合群
where he was a consistently lousy student,
没有家人和朋友
one without friends or a loving family
给他丝毫的温暖和鼓励
to provide any warmth or encouragement.
牛顿不与人交流  把自己关在房间里
Newton mostly kept to himself, sequestered in his room,
学习古希腊的哲学
studying ancient Greek philosophers,
几何和语言
geometry and languages,
琢磨着更深层次的问题
and pondering deep questions
关于自然  空间  时间  运动
on the nature of matter, space, time, and motion.
这位才华初露的科学家也是一名狂热的神秘主义者
This budding scientist was also a passionate mystic.
牛顿相信这种只为小部分
Newton believed that a secret knowledge
古代哲学家所知的炼金术
called alchemy, known only to a small group of ancient philosophers,
正等着他去重新发现
was waiting to be rediscovered.
他希望可以学会把普通金属
He hoped to learn how to change ordinary metals
变成金银的方法
into silver and gold,
或许可以做出生命合剂
and maybe even cook up the elixir of life,
以此长生不老
the key to to immortality.
他一心想从圣经的字里行间
He was also obsessed
找到隐藏的信息
with finding hidden messages in the words of the Bible.
他梳理了不用语言的译本
He combed through translations in several different languages,
试图破译加密了的上帝的指示
hoping to decipher coded instructions from God.
他做了详尽的计算
He made elaborate calculations in an effort
只为发现基督再次降临的日期
to discover the date of the Second Coming.
穷其一生研究炼金术
His lifelong research in alchemy
研究圣经  可惜没有任何突破
and biblical chronology never led anywhere.
当哈雷找到牛顿的那天
When Halley found Newton that fateful day,
牛顿一直过着隐居的生活
he was living as a virtual recluse.
牛顿自从罗伯特・胡克公开指责他
Newton had gone into hiding 13 years earlier,
剽窃胡克关于光学和颜色的突破性成果
after Robert Hooke had publicly accused Newton of stealing
已经隐居了13年
his groundbreaking work on light and color.
事实上 牛顿才是那个
In fact, it was Isaac Newton
解开光谱谜团的人
who solved the mystery of the spectrum of light,
并不是罗伯特・胡克
not Robert Hooke.
这对他的打击很大
This wound was painful and deep,
牛顿下定决心从此再不让自己陷入
and Newton resolved to never expose himself to that kind
那种被人羞辱的境地
of public humiliation ever again.
先生 你可能不记得了
Sir, I don't suppose you recall
我们几年前见过
our meeting a few years ago?
我记得 哈雷先生
Yes, Mr. Halley.
抱歉来打搅你
I'm sorry to bother you.
不用客套 有话直说
Never mind the formalities, get to your point.
我一直与我们的朋友  胡克和雷恩在讨论
I've been talking with our friends, Mr. Wren and Mr. Hooke.
胡克那个人渣不是我的朋友
That scoundrel Hooke's no friend of mine.
我明白
Yes, I understand, sir.
重点是 我们一直在讨论
But the thing is we've been debating
行星运动的难题
the puzzling question of planetary motion.
我们都认同 某种吸引的力量
We all agree that some force of attraction
来自太阳  控制着行星的运动
from the Sun governs the motions of the planets.
我们感觉一定能有一条数学定律
We suspect there must be a mathematical law
来形容这种
to describe how this force
根据距离而改变的力量
changes with distance.
以您的能力
And knowing of your skill...
没错 重力所产生的吸引力
Yes, yes, the attraction of gravity
与距离的平方成反比
weakens with the square of the distance.
这就是椭圆轨道的原因
That's why the planets move in ellipses.
但您是怎么知道的
But, sir, how can you know this?
怎么了 我5年多前就算出来了
Why, I have calculated it some five years ago.
求你了 让我见识一下
I beg you, show it to me.
计算的结果在这里
The calculation is here...
就在周围
somewhere.
没关系
Well, no matter.
我重新做一份
I shall redo it and be sure
然后寄给你
to send it on to you.
太不可思议了
This is stupendous!
相见恨晚啊
Why have we not had word of it before?
牛顿还记得上次
Newton remembered all too well
他提出新的理论时
what Hooke had done to him
胡克的所作所为
the last time he put forth an idea.
就在哈雷开始怀疑
Just when Halley may have begun to wonder
牛顿是否也像胡克那样吹牛时
if Newton was bluffing as Hooke had done earlier,
信使带来牛顿的一封信
a messenger arrived with an envelope from Newton.
这是现代科学理论的开篇
Here are the opening pages of modern science
包含了对于大自然的洞察
with its all-embracing vision of nature...
运动定律  万有引力
universal laws of motion, gravity...
不单适用于地球
not just for the Earth,
也适用于整个宇宙
but for the cosmos.
哈雷迫不及待地回到剑桥
Halley raced back to Cambridge.
牛顿大人  我求你赶紧
Mr. Newton, I beseech you to work all of this
把这些都写进你的书里吧
into a book as soon as possible.
我向你保证 皇家学一定会出版你的书
I can assure you the Royal Society will publish it.
但还有一个小问题
But there was one little problem.
我们同意
We are in agreement
牛顿先生的成果是伟大的
that Mr. Newton has produced a masterpiece.
但是  皇家学会恐怕
However, I'm afraid the Royal Society has...
因为《鱼类历史》的惨淡销售
well, regrettably sales for the History of Fish...
造成我们的财政状况并不乐观
have not lived up to our financial expectations.
这是一本很棒的书
It's an impressive book.
包罗万象
Extremely comprehensive.
真的
Really.
使用了大量的插图来描述
It's filled with lavish illustrations of...
鱼类
well, fish.
销量惨淡带来更大的问题
The disappointing sales led to a bigger problem.
就是皇家学会在出版《鱼类历史》上
The Royal Society pretty much blew
几乎花了整年的预算
its total annual budget on the History of Fish.
他们现金短缺
In fact, they were so strapped for cash,
他们不得不用那卖不掉的书
they had to pay poor Halley's salary
来抵本应支付给哈雷的工资
with copies of their worst-selling book.
没有钱来印刷牛顿的《原理》
With no money to print Newton's Principia,
科学革命 命悬一线
the scientific revolution hung in the balance.
要不是哈雷的努力
Without Halley's heroic efforts,
牛顿的这部巨著
the reclusive Newton's masterwork
可能永无出头之日
might never have seen the light of day.
哈雷的坚持不懈
But Halley was a man on a mission,
将牛顿的天才展现给了全世界
absolutely determined to bring Newton's genius to the world.
那个科学革命以前
That pre-scientific world,
靠恐惧来统治的世界
the world ruled by fear,
已经被推向了革命的边缘
was poised at the edge of a revolution.
一切就看爱德蒙・哈雷能否
Everything depended on whether or not Edmond Halley
将牛顿的新书推向世界
could get Newton's book out to the wider world.
哈雷编辑并且出版了牛顿的书
Halley resolved not only to edit Newton's book,
全都自掏腰包
but to publish it at his own expense.
在牛顿完成的头两卷里
Newton completed the first two volumes,
用数学公式
laying the mathematical framework
来描述物理运动
for the physics of motion.
第三卷彻底决定了谁才是咖啡馆的
The third volume would settle once and for all
赌局赢家
who won the coffeehouse wager.
牛顿运用他的原理可以解释
Newton applied his principles to explain
地球上所有的运动
all the known motions of the Earth,
月亮和其它行星
the Moon and the planets.
不幸的是 还有一个问题
Unfortunately, there was this problem.
哈雷又变成了
Now Halley also took on the role
牛顿的心理医生
of Newton's psychotherapist.
艾萨克  那个  胡克先生要求
Isaac, I'm afraid that Mr. Hooke requires
在你的第三卷序言里向他致谢
an acknowledgment in the preface of your third volume.
我已经做过了啊
But I have done so.
谢谢他 雷恩先生还有你
Thanking him, Mr. Wren and yourself
激励我重新思考有关天文学的事情
for prodding me to think again on astronomical matters.
胡克在伦敦到处说
Mr. Hooke has been going about London saying
你的万有引力定律是借鉴了他
that you got the Law of Gravity from him.
我要告他这个小...
Why, that litigious little...
做梦
Never!
我宁可烧了我的第三卷
I would sooner burn the third volume
也不会让这种谎言玷污它
than deface it with such a lie.
让胡克去死吧
To hell with Hooke.
他会被人们遗忘
He will be long forgotten
而你的理论会被人们永远歌颂
when your ideas are still being celebrated.
又是这些恶心的书
More copies of that dreadful book?
家里都快放不下了
Wherever shall we put them all?
我和你说过的 玛丽 亲爱的
We talked about this, Mary, dear.
这是科学院给我的薪水
This is my salary from the Society.
他们也拿不出其它东西了
They have nothing else with which to pay me.
如果胡克和牛顿也能像你这样就好了
If only Mr. Hooke and Mr. Newton were more like you.
哈雷和雷恩决定和胡克对质
Halley and Wren decided to confront Hooke
关于他不实的言论
about his false claims.
那是我的定律 我告诉你
That law is mine, I tell you!
我先证明的
I proved it first.
那就把你的证据拿出来
Then fetch your proof here at once.
让我们看看
Let us see it.
反正我们都等了这么久了
Surely we have waited on it long enough.
你只要相信我的话就可以了
You'll simply have to take my word for it.
空口无凭或许在其它地方行得通
Empty claims may persuade elsewhere,
但这里不行
but not here.
"勿轻信人言"
拿不出来就闭嘴  胡克先生
Put up or shut up, Mr. Hooke.
牛顿这个混蛋  我要他付出代价
Blasted Newton. I'll make him pay.
"自然哲学的数学原理"
如果没有爱德蒙・哈雷
If it wasn't for Edmond Halley,
牛顿绝没有机会构思
Newton's great book would've never been conceived,
书写 出版他的书
nor written, nor printed.
好吧  那又怎样
Okay. So what?
对我们来说有什么不一样
What difference does that make to us?
有什么大不了的
What's the big deal?
当牛顿在这栋房子里诞生时
When Isaac Newton was born in this house
1642年  那是的世界和现在完全不一样
in 1642, the world was very different.
每个人看到天空中的众多星星
Everyone looked at the perfection
像钟表一样极有规律的准确运行
of the clockwork motions of the planets in the sky
只能想到的是出自
and could only understand it as the work
一个伟大的「钟表匠」
of a master clock maker.
还能怎么解释
How else to explain it?
他们只能想出一种解释
There was only one way such a thing could come about
以他们的想象力
in their imagination;
只有一种答案
only one answer for them--
上帝
God.
出于我们还不了解的原因
For reasons beyond our understanding,
上帝就是这么创造的太阳系
God just created the solar system that way.
这个解释却是一个死结
But this explanation is the closing of a door.
并无法解释其它的问题
It doesn't lead to other questions.
牛顿来了
Along came Newton,
上帝宠爱的人  大天才
a God-loving man who's also a genius.
他能用完美的数学语句
He could write the laws of nature
写出大自然的定律
in perfect mathematical sentences--
对宇宙有效的方程式
formulas that applied universally
对苹果 月亮 行星都有效
to apples, moons, planets
还有很多
and so much more.
虽然仍身处中世纪
With one foot still in the Middle Ages,
牛顿已经想象出了整个太阳系
Isaac Newton imagined the whole solar system.
牛顿的万有引力和运动定律
Newton's laws of gravity and motion
揭示了太阳如何维系这些遥远的星球
revealed how the Sun held distant worlds captive.
他的定律使人们不再需要
His laws swept away the need
用「钟表匠」来解释
for a master clock maker
为什么太阳系能如此精准的运行
to explain the precision and beauty of the solar system.
万有引力就是钟表匠
Gravity is the clock maker.
事物遵循我们发现的戒律运动
Matter obeyed commandments we could discover,
遵循圣经没有提到过的定律运动
laws the Bible hadn't mentioned.
牛顿的理论解释了为什么太阳子会是这样的
Newton's answer to why the solar system is the way it is
也为其它无数的问题打开了大门
opened the way to an infinite number of questions.
《原理》的内容里包括
Principia also happened to include
微积分的发明
the invention of calculus,
还有第一个坚实的理论基础
and the first sound theoretical basis
为我们打破了地球的枷锁
for an end to our imprisonment on Earth--
太空旅行
space travel.
牛顿设想 发射出去的炮弹
Newton envisioned the firing of a cannonball...
随着爆炸推力的增加
with increasingly greater explosive thrust.
只要速度足够快
He reasoned that with enough velocity,
就可以突破引力的界限
the bounds of gravity could be broken,
炮弹就可以离开地球
and the cannonball could escape
绕地球旋转
to orbit the Earth.
这 改变了 整个世界
This changed everything.
牛顿的数学原理 将我们彻底解放
Newton's Principia Mathematica set us free in another way.
通过找到控制彗星运行的自然定律
By finding the natural laws governing the comings and goings of comets,
他使我们不再像祖先那样
he decoupled the motions of the heavens
恐惧天体运行
from their ancient connections to our fears.
如果哈雷没有竭尽全力的支持牛顿
If Halley hadn't been standing next to Newton for all those years,
人们可能会记住他自己的发现和成就
perhaps the world would remember him for his own accomplishments and discoveries.
而不是 仅仅记住一个彗星的名字
But the only thing that comes to mind for most people
讽刺的是  发现彗星这件事
is the comet, the irony is that discovering a comet
其实哈雷从没有做过
is actually one of the few things that Halley never did.
有冰山
Mountain of ice to starboard
左满舵
Come about
报告哈雷队长
Aye, aye, Captain Halley!
《原理》出版后
After the publication of the Principia
哈雷奉命带领3艘大船  出海科学考察
Halley was commanded by his king to lead three ocean voyages,
为英国海军解决导航的问题
scientific expeditions to solve navigational problems for the British navy.
哈雷利用这次机会  绘制了第一张地球磁场图
Halley used this opportunity to make the first map of the Earth's magnetic field
他同时也是个商人
And he was also a businessman.
哈雷改良了潜水钟
Halley perfected the diving bell...
并用他的发明
...and used his invention to start
开创了繁荣的商业打捞业务
a flourishing commercial salvage operation.
嗯 哈雷博士这次是真的做到了
Mmm, ah, Dr. Halley's gone and done it this time.
我看他在下面最少3个小时了
I reckon he's been down there at least three hours.
没人拿其它人的生命冒险
Not one to risk the lives of others,
哈雷亲自测试他的发明
Halley personally tested his own invention.
下来以后已经坚持了4个小时
I make it exactly four hours since our descent.
对10英寻的深度来说不错了
Not at all bad for ten fathoms.
10英寻等于约18米
他发明了气象图
He invented the weather map.
他设计的标示盛行风的符号
And the symbols he devised for indicating prevailing winds
一直沿用至今
are still in use today.
星期一天气预测
世界天气
哈雷为人口统计学
Halley laid the groundwork
打下了坚实的基础
for the science of population statistics.
怎么做的
How?
他对比伦敦和巴黎的出生 结婚 死亡人数
He compared the birth, marriage, death,
以及人口密度
and population densities of London and Paris.
他真的用双脚
He actually had to pace off
测量出巴黎的周长
the entire perimeter of Paris, on foot,
只为计算正确的面积
to learn its true dimensions.
他总结出
He came to the conclusion
既然大约一半的成年人
that since roughly half of all adults fail
无法生孩子
to reproduce children,
要延续他们繁衍的基因
who themselves survive to reproduce,
每对夫妻必须要有4个孩子
every married couple must have four children
才能保持人口数量
in order to maintain the population.
爱德蒙 哈雷告诉我们
And it was Edmond Halley who gave us
太阳系的实际比例
the actual scale of the solar system.
他找到一个聪明的办法算出
He figured out a clever way to find the distance
地球到太阳的距离
from Earth to the Sun.
通过精确地测量
It involved precisely measuring the time it took
金星穿过日面所用的时间
for the planet Venus to cross the Sun's disc.
即金星凌日
哈雷过世后的27年
27 years after Halley's death,
詹姆士库克船长第一次到达塔希提岛
Captain James Cook made his first voyage to Tahiti
为了验证哈雷的方法
for the express purpose of testing Halley's method
在观察在金星凌日的过程中
during a transit of Venus across the Sun.
他用一种特殊的滤镜保护眼睛
Using a special filter to protect his vision
防止直视太阳带来的损伤
from being destroyed by looking directly at the Sun,
库克团队的努力使我们知道
Cook and his men made it possible for us to know
约为1.5亿公里
太阳距离地球9300万英里
that the Sun is 93 million miles from Earth.
哈雷也是第一个认识到
And Halley was the first to realize
所谓的恒星 并非静止不动
that the so-called "fixed" stars were not fixed at all.
他是怎么知道的
How'd he do it?
他将古希腊天文学家
He pored over the observations made
对最明亮的星星的观测结果
by the ancient Greek astronomers of the brightest stars.
与他在1800年后观测的同一颗星星的
And he compared their observations with the ones
观测结果作比较
he himself made of the same stars 1,800 years later.
为什么之前没人注意到
Why hadn't anyone noticed this before?
哈雷意识到要想观察出来
Halley figured out that it would only become apparent
两次的观测时间要间隔很长才行
if you waited long enough between observations.
要观察到相距遥远的物体间的移动
It's hard to perceive the motions of things
是很困难的
that are far away.
而且恒星间的距离是如此的遥远
And the stars are so very far away,
要花几百年的时间去观察
that you would need to track them for many centuries
才能察觉他们的移动
before you could detect that they moved at all.
哈雷发现了一个宏伟的现实
Halley discovered the first clue to a magnificent reality,
所有的恒星都在运动 相互赶超
all the stars are in motion, streaming past each other,
和旋转木马一样上升和降落
rising and falling like merry-go-round horses
在银河系中此起彼伏
in their Newtonian dance around the center of our galaxy.
对了 还有彗星的事情
And, oh, yes, there was that thing about the comet.
这些美丽的陌生天外访客到底是谁
What were those strange and beautiful celestial visitors
时不时的突然造访
that appeared without warning from time to time?
哈雷用侦探常用的方法来解决这个谜团
Halley set out to solve this mystery as a detective would,
搜集所有可靠目击证人的证词
by gathering all credible eyewitness testimony.
哈雷能找到的最早准确观察到
The earliest precise observations of a comet
彗星的证人是位于君士坦丁堡的
that Halley could find were made in Constantinople
尼斯波罗斯・贵格列 拜占庭帝国的天文学家兼僧人
by Nikephoros Gregoras, a Byzantine astronomer and monk
1337年6月
in June 1337.
哈雷收集了1472-1698年间所有的
Halley hunted down every astronomical observation
在欧洲的彗星观测记录
of a comet recorded in Europe between 1472 and 1698.
请记住 那时还没有
And remember, there was no such thing
搜索引擎 或者计算机
as a search engine or a computer.
哈雷只能依靠他的书和大脑
All Halley had were his books and his mind.
困难的地方到了
Now here comes the hard part,
哈雷必须要按照每个彗星的观察结果
Halley had to take the observations made for each comet
在太空中的找出实际的运动轨迹
and find the shape of its actual path through space.
除了牛顿 没人尝试过
No one else but Newton had yet attempted
将他的定律应用于天文学的问题
to apply his new set of laws to an astronomical question.
这是一次艰巨的数学运算的壮举
In an arduous tour de force of mathematical brilliance,
哈雷发现彗星被太阳束缚在
Halley discovered that comets were bound to the Sun
长椭圆的轨道上
in long elliptical orbits.
他是第一个知道1531年发现的那个彗星
And he was the first to know that the comets seen in 1531,
和1607年 还有1682年发现的
1607, and 1682...
是同一颗彗星
were one and the same--
每隔76年回归一次
a single comet that returned every 76 years.
这是识别规律的绝佳例子
In a stunning example of true pattern recognition,
他预测彗星还会回归
he predicted it would be seen again
在超过50年后的未来
more than 50 years in the future.
上千年来 彗星都很神秘
For millennia, comets had been props for mystics,
被巫师们视为人类事件的预兆
who considered them to be merely omens of human events.
哈雷打破了他们的垄断
Halley shattered their monopoly,
以他们熟悉的领域里
beating them at their own game,
以前没有科学家进入过的领域
a game that no scientist had ever played before...
预言
prophecy.
他没有闪烁其词
And he did not hedge his bet.
就像贝比・鲁斯预测
Like Babe Ruth predicting
他的下一个全垒打会落在哪里
where his next home run would land in the stands,
哈雷明确地指出这颗彗星
Halley stated flatly that the comet would return
会在1758年底 出现在天空中的一个特定位置
at the end of 1758, from a particular part of the sky,
遵循一条特定的轨迹
following a specific path.
几乎没有一个由巫师提出的预言
There is hardly a prophecy attempted by the mystics
能和他的准确性相提并论
that ever even strives for comparable precision.
这就是 哈雷彗星
That's Halley's Comet.
漂浮在太阳系的边缘
Out here at the edge of the solar system,
看上去并不大
it doesn't look like much.
只是太空中一块冰石
Just a big hunk of ice and rock in space.
因为在海王星的轨道以外
That's because beyond the orbit of Neptune,
距离太阳大约50亿公里
nearly five billion kilometers from the Sun,
彗星过得非常宁静
comets lead very quiet lives.
因为到达了轨道的远程
As it reaches the far end of its orbit,
它会慢下来 直到太阳将它拉回来
it'll slow down till the Sun allows it to go no farther.
然后它向太阳系的核心坠落
Then it will begin its long fall back to the inner solar system.
哈雷彗星绕着太阳做自由落体
Halley's comet is in free fall around the Sun.
太阳系中的一切  地球  月亮
Everything in our solar system-- the Earth, the Moon,
其它行星  彗星  小行星
the other planets, comets, asteroids,
都绕着太阳自由落体
all of them are falling around the Sun.
万有引力将他们拉向太阳
Gravity pulls the planets towards the Sun,
但因为他们的轨道动量
but because of their orbital momentum,
他们保持环绕太阳  而不冲向太阳
they keep moving around the Sun, never falling into it.
罗伯特・胡克很多年前过世了
Robert Hooke had died years before,
一些坏习惯伤害了他的健康
having ruined his health with some bad habits...
天天服用苦艾 鸦片 水银
daily doses of wormwood, opium, mercury.
几个月后  牛顿取代了他的职位
A few months later, Newton was elected to replace him
当选皇家学会的会长
as president of the Royal Society.
据说胡克的肖像
It is said that a portrait of Hooke
曾经挂在这里
once hung on these walls.
哈雷达成了很多天文学的丰功伟绩
Halley lived on to accomplish many more astonishing feats.
他坚持工作到最后一刻 享年85岁
He worked right up to his death at age 85.
他做的最后一件事是叫了一杯葡萄酒
His final act was to call for a glass of wine.
愉快的品下
He downed it with pleasure...
呼出最后一口气
and breathed his last breath.
据信在这样的一个夜里
Some believe that it was on a night like this
艾萨克牛顿终于实施了他对
that Isaac Newton finally took his revenge
罗伯特胡克的报复
against Robert Hooke.
哈雷的预言并未被人遗忘
But Halley's prophecy was not forgotten.
50年后
50 years later,
就在预言回归的时间
as the time of the predicted return approached,
全世界的天文学家都希望
the world's astronomers vied
第一个观察到 哈雷的彗星
to be the first to catch sight of his comet.
他们没有失望
They weren't disappointed.
从此以后 每隔76年都有一次观测热潮
It's been welcomed back every 76 years since.
当哈雷彗星回到我们的天空时
When Halley's Comet returns to our skies,
日光加热它表面的冰
sunlight will warm up the ice on its surface,
再一次释放出
once again setting loose
内部的灰尘和气体
the dust and gases trapped within.
哈雷彗星的最近一次回归
Halley's Comet most recently visited our neighborhood
是1986年
back in 1986.
如果你在2061年看到这个
And if you're seeing this in 2061,
你就知道 它回来了
then you'll know it's back.
愿你看到眼前的这些
May you feel the wonder of all those
令人惊叹的奇迹时
who came before you...
不再害怕
and none of the fear.
牛顿定律使爱德蒙哈雷可以预见
Newton's laws made it possible for Edmond Halley
50年后的未来
to see some 50 years into the future
预测一颗彗星的运动轨迹
and predict the behavior of a single comet.
科学家们一直使用这些定律
Scientists have been using these laws ever since,
打开通往月球之路
opening the way to the Moon
乃至整个太阳系
and even beyond our solar system.
摇篮中的婴儿开始学习走路了
The baby in the basket is learning to walk...
开始了解宇宙
and to know the cosmos.
还有最后一个预言
Which brings me to one last prophecy.
仅仅依靠牛顿的万有引力定律
Using nothing more than Newton's laws of gravitation,
天文学家可以很确定的预测
we astronomers can confidently predict
几十亿年后
that several billion years from now,
我们的星系  银河系
our home galaxy, the Milky Way,
会与我们的邻居 仙女座 交汇
will merge with our neighboring galaxy Andromeda.
因为恒星间的距离
Because the distances between the stars
相对他们的体积来说 是如此的遥远
are so great compared to their sizes,
只会有很少数的星星发生碰撞
few if any stars in either galaxy will actually collide.
遥远未来 依然存在的生命
Any life on the worlds of that far-off future
应该很安全  但是他们可以欣赏到
should be safe, but they would be treated to an amazing,
持续几十亿年的星光秀
billion-year-long light show...
几千亿颗星星的群舞
a dance of a half a trillion stars...
还有一位伟人与他的挚友共同谱写的精彩乐章
to music first heard on one little world by a man who had but one true friend.